<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-amelia-bloomer</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86071377/1851-08-14/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Bloomer+Bloomerism</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Iew Costume.
Mr. Editor: In the Sentinel of July Cist, I
observe the communication of Sancho, agaiast
the Bloomer Costume. It appears I threw
down the gauntlet and he picked it up. I
certainly bid him welcome in the ring. I did
indeed expect him to advocate the old mole of
dress, and show wherein it is superior and more
adapted to the comfort of woman than the con
templated change, but sad disappointment
awaited me. In my communication a few wetks
ago, I stated (and by the way it is admitted by
most ladies,) that the present mode of dress
is not the best that could be adopted, and that
Reform in female costume was necessary. Hence
the onus probands lies on Sancho's shoulders,
and he should have shown wherein it is that the
present mode of female dress adds so much
-grace ana dignity to tne lady, but he is
1
8transel7 afnt oa this subject.
I have read
Sancho's article again and again, and am at last
1 -6" &amp;'-i"
constrain ea to exclaim with Bassanio in the
constrained to exclaim
r
Merchant of Venice, "bis arguments are like
two grains of wheat in two bushels of chaff,
you must search all to find them, and after you
have found them they are not worthy your
search." Sancho makes a few beautiful rheto-
flourishes, and no doubt when he wrote
ti3 articic on Bloomerism he must have been
inspired with the chivabric spirit of Don Quix
otte. It is a very fine thing to talk about
fame," "sword," "pen" and "sweet nonsense,"
but what all these things have to do with the
present subject under consideration it is difficult
for me to Conceive, unless Sancho thinks that
by making use of such "heroic" epithets he will
bo able to drive the friends of the Bloomer
costume from the field, and thus make himself
sole umpire of the world of fashion.
We shall now briefly notice a few of Sancho's
remarks. He says Mrs. Bloomer proposes a
complete and sudden transformation of the
present dress worn by ladies." Well is it wrong
that Mrs. Bloomer should do so If the present
mode of female dress is not the best that could
be worn, and Sancho does not deny the fact, is
it not perfectly consonant with reason and
common sense that a change should take place
in the world of female fashion! Again ho says,
"It (the new dress) is undeniably pretty' for a
Harem girl or ballet dancer; but no less unsuit
able for an enlightened woman," &amp;c. Ah, in
deed! How does Sancho know it would be un
suitable for an "enlightened" woman. This is
simply an ipse dixit without any proof to sus
tain it. We have it from the lips of intelligent
laoies who say that the new dress is very suit
able we also have the opinions of eminent
physicians, who say that tho dress now worn by
ladies is very injurious to health
And is this no proof positive Are we not to
take the opinions of men who are capable of
judging!
I am of the opinion that Mrs. Bloomer com
pares favorably with Sancho's female friend in
intelligence, whose language Ue quotes. Cut let
Mrs. ElnnmPi. nek for herself. Below is an
extract of a letter written by her to the N. Y.
Tribune.
"Many seem to think if we shorten our
dresses just enough to permit them to pass over
cigar-stubs, tobacco juice, and other nitn, tnas
is all that is necessary to be done, lou, sir, i
believe, entertain that opinion. But we who
know from experience the evils of lone skirts
even though they fall no lower than the ankle
and the blossioes of short ones, can
not aeree with those who think thus. The
longer the dress, the greater the quantity of
underskirts needed to give us a good figure;
the shorter the dress the greater the number
and weight dispensed with.
If we wear long dresses, we must from ne
cessity wear a considerable amount of under
clothing; for even a lady in short dress and
trousers does not appear so decidedly immodest
and vulgar, as does she with a lonz one cline
ing close to her form, and whipping about her
limbs. By shortening our skirts two or three
inches we might save them wiping up filth from
the Btreet; but they are 'just as cumbersome
and crippling as the longer ones; whereas, by
shortening them nearly to the knee, we not only
give freedom and elasticity to our limbs, but re
lieve ourselves of the undue weight hitherto
suspended from the waist.
We may look more graceful in the draseline
skirt, but weee more graceful in the short
one.
The only question in regard to the new cos
tume, should be as to its utility; and there are
enough of us who can speak from experience
on that point. Custom will make any. dress
look well and already, to my eye, the Ameri
can short dress and trousers appears more truly
graceful and genteel, than the long, mopping,
crippling drapery."
We now ask Sancho to read the opinion of a
physician on the subject of the new dress
"But I have stronger reasons professional
and scientific for siding with the reformers,
among which are the following the use of long
dresses, implies, as a general thine, the use of
stays, thus leading to consumption and a host
of other diseases; the use of said ungainly
costume is incompatible with exercise, to any
extent, and therefore tends to injury of the
muscular system, as well as of the nervous and
circulatory. The quantity of skirt and prodi
gality of nnder-garments infallibly destroys the
figure, and frequently induces lumbar abscess, or
general spinous affection. The tm-dewy fluids j
and vn-Lubinized extracts collected by the long
flowing garments and from them in part trans
mitted to the inferior portion of the lower ex
tremities, throws back the blood from the sur
face of the skin, thus engendering cold and itj
many distressing and fatal results.
I do not wish Woman to unsex herself. But
she may become rational without becominir
masculine. Is she not rational then one
cries I answer, She has reason surel r, but she
does not exercise it at present. Reason and
long skirts could not be co-existent: Reason
and draggle-tails are sternly opposed. Reason
does not admit the legitimacy of boddices
(tightly laced) and is a foe to artificial disease
on principle. Beasoa considers a sound body
preferable to a Grecian bend," and prefers
being in good health to being in the fashion. In
the name of reason, then, loosen the 6Uy -strings
and shorten the skirts."
Does Sancho still think the New Costume
unsuitable for an "enlightened" woman Does
Sancho mean to say that none but ignorant la-
lies have adopted the Lluumer costume "Ani
since it is clearly proved," says he, "that nei
ther health nor comfort are advanced by it, no
lady of good taste would lay aside the graceful
and dignified long dress fur the doll baby attire
of Mrs. Bloomer." How exccedinelv modest!
Has Mrs. Bloomer no taste! Clear proofs!
Where are they! Will Sancho give us his idea
of the physician's opinion we quote, and then
say whether the Bloomer costume is only doll
baby attire" I particularly invite the atten
tion of the reader to Sancho's closing remarks.
And, Oh, gentle reader! did you ever read any
thing more sublime! Sancho no doubt imagined
that he had a wife a disciple of Mrs. Bloomer
and that he was treated badly. Oh, ye gods
and little fishes Let not Sancho's fate be that
which flitted across his imagination, when he
bowed at the shrine of anti-Bloomerism. Mav
he have a gentle, loving wife, one after the im
age of his own heart, one that will look with
horror upon the friends of the New Costume,
and though she may be able to wear the bree
ches" in petticoats, and smoke cigars, play
cards, &amp;c. Dear Editor, I here leave the sub
ject with you and your readers</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026536/1852-07-30/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=bloomer+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Whar'a the Bloomer?
Empires rise and fall, flourish and decay, and so
do styles of dress. The w Bloomer," however, has
had a brief existence- the election canvass has come
on and cut it short off although it was reasonal ly
short before and behind too, for that matter. We
no longer read about the Bloomer," and amidst all
the electioneering platforms that have been got up.
there is no Bloomer platform. Perhaps, though,
the Bloomer shows conspicuous enough on a dead
level without any platform to stand upon.
But it is gone and faded the last and only Bloom
has paraded our streets the reign of tyranny and
proscription is again reinstated, and women and
men both must submit to petticoat rule. So mote
it. It is only in Mormondom that this Turkish style
could have any real permanence for the Mormons
have the substance as well as the shadow they not
only adopt the Turkish costume, but also adhere to
the Turkish manners and have several wives. Lucky
or unlucky fellows, those Mormons, as the case may
be. Solomons in their way the Solomons of the
Salt lake.
But the Bloomer was a real political affair as the
world goes. It was not troubled with two much
modesty. 1 stuck out and commended itself to the
attention of the public. It kicked up a bobbery
sure, ami thought itself famous. It took noise for
applause, as many others have done. Whar's the
Bloomer now Laid up in some several trunks
hung upon various pegs the unthinkable-abouts
turned into summer pants for some little brother,
the skirts, etc., razeed into dresses for the smaller
fry or turned to some less honorable use. All gone
and a dead failure.
Dearly beloved hearers, there is a lesson in the
fate of the bloomer. Beware of its fate. Beware
of exalting things too high, or of thinking too high
ly of yourself. Innovations must come gradually.
Men and women, though not peculiarly the slaves
of custom, are not apt to jump into direct opposi
tion to established customs, or to suppose that every
man or woman who opposes such must necessarily
be benefactors of their race. Change is not always
improvement,: factionanes whether politics, reli
gion or costume are not necessarily patriots saints,
or such like. There are a great many big profes
sions being made now-a-days. It is not often that
sincerity deals in such. Beware
If we have broken in upon the seriousness of po
litical discussions for a few moments, we hope to be
excused. Perhaps even out of this folly some lessons
might be learned some hints taken. At any rate,
we have a right to indulge ourselves witu some re
laxation, and therefore have made, and now repeat
the enquiry whar's the Bloomer?</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85026203/1853-02-25/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Amelia+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Woman's Tkmpesanck Mektino. A rnact
ing, having for its object the advincemnnt of
tbe temperance cause, was held on Monday
evening at the Metroplitah Hull. It having
been announced that Mrs.- Amelia Bloomer and
several other ''strong minded" women from the
interior of the State, would be present and ad.
dress the meeting, a large number of ladies and
gentlemen, attracted by the novelty of the
thine, assembled, and. the hall was almost en.
tirely tilled, At half pst 7 o'clock tbe orators
appeared ou the platform anil were loudly greet
ed. They Wore Mrs. Amelia Bloomer, Rev.
Antoinette D own, Miss Suan B. Anthouy,
and Miat L. N. Fowlor. Mrs., Bluomer and
Miss Anthony were the only ones of the party
attired in the llloomer costume. The former
was dressed in a dark brown tunic, descending
to the knees, the skirt trimmed with rows of
black velvet. Her dress had An open corsage,
ilh band of velvet over the white chemisette
in which was a diamond, stud -and pins. She
wore flowing sleeves, tight nnderaleevci,' and
black lace mitts. The pautuloons were of tbe
same texture as tbe tunic, and trimmed in the
same style. The dres of the latter wjs some
what plainer, and con.nsied or a black brocade
silk tunic, with pjtits of the tame mateiiul.
Her hair was out abort, somewhat in the isah-
ion of the male habitues of Broadway.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86091172/1887-08-19/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Amelia+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Be
fore her, Mrs. Amelia Bloomer, nearly
40 years ago, set the example of
abott, loose dresses.
The style was adopted bv many
women, Among them Mrs. Elizabeth
Cady StattXoo; Miss Susan B. An
thony, and the present writer. How
light and oomfcrtsble and neat it was!
How easily we went up stairs without
Stepping on ourselves! How we came
down stairs without fear of being
stepped on! A walk on rainy day
Or in muddy street had no terror,
hi* there were no yards of draggled
skfrts to clesu. We hsd room to
breathe, and freedom for nur feet.
But this healthful dress was "deipiSed
and Rejected" by the great public.
On one Occasion, Miaa Anthony, in
company With me, started to go to
tha postofBoe in New York, in the
Bloomer eosttime. Bot we were aur
rounded and feedired in bv a crowd
__ r
Which hooted Ma jeered. We
eaoed only by a tarri.ge sent by a
friend who saw our dilemma. i
U I
wa» so ilimcult to wear this dress, 1
wiih the odium that was cast upon it,
that we leturned sorrowfully to the
bondage of our bodies for the sake of
freedom to live unmolested. Thsi
was long ago. Now women might
accept the light, sensible dress which
Mrs. Jenness-Miller wears and com
mends, without fear of unpleasaut
comment.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn94051692/1893-06-29/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Amelia+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The New
York Evening Sun instances bloomer
costume, which wai organized and pro
moted by Mrs. Amelia Bloomer, now a
hard-working woman in long skirts
out west. </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025308/1893-08-13/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Amelia+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>More than 40 years ago Amelia Bloomer
began an agitation for the reform of the
dress of women on both awsthetic and sani
tary grounds. She did not- content herself
with meeregeneral suggestions, bu.t atlpted
end advocated a particular costu n devised
and first worn by a dlaughter of G;ertit
Smith, one of the early abolitionists. Her
example was followed by Mrs. Elizabelth
Cady S.tanton, Lucy Stone and others of
the women's rights revolutiontis i llBut
the Bloomler costumec, as it ctanltt to be
called, dli not receive fetmiuine favor, and
soon evell those who were self sacrificing
enough to make the experiment of wearing
it in the face of public derision were glad
to discard the ugly garmeunts and to render
ienewed submitsion to the imperious dic
tates of conventional fashion.
.The costume did not satisfy the taste of
Mr. Gladstone for flowing Grecian draper
fes, but was devised for the very purpose of
getting rid of them as obstructive of the
free movement of women, and the reform
dress recommended at Chicago only lately
is constructed on the same general prin
ciples. In each there is it tunic reachieng to
tihe knee or a little below, and then cotme
trousers or leggings. loth bear some sort
of resemlblance to the present feminine
bathing costume, except that they lose its
grace and beauty by concealing the contour
of the lower legs with baggy coverings in
stead of revealing it with close litting
stockings. The new reform dress was in
troduced into the women's convention at
Chicago and excited much curiosity as
worn by two or lthree of its courageous ad
vocates, but we have not heard that even
they have ventured to wear it hiabitually in
Ipublic, and if they did so probably they
would provoke no less derision than Mr is.
Amelia Bloomer and her refortmatory asso
ciates excitedl a generation ago.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85030821/1894-10-26/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=Amelia+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MOTHER OF BLOOMERS.
The Woman After Whom the
Garment
Was Christened.
Mrs. Amelia Bloomer, after whom
the garment known as the bloomer
costume was christened, resides with
her husband in Council Bluffs, their
residence to-day being the one in
which they took up their abode forty
years ago. when Council Bluffs, was a
somewhat straggling village of 300.
Mrs. Bloomer, now 76 years old, carries
her years easily. She has been married
fifty -four years. It was in 1851 that
she began to wear the costume which
is now known throughout the English
speaking world as
the bloomer. She
was then living at
Seneca Falls, N. Y.
where -she pub
lished a temper
ance paper called
the Lily. In addi
tion to being a pro
hibition advocate
the paper also de
voted considerable
space to the sub
AMELIA BLOOMER
ject of woman suffrage. A Mrs. Mil
ler, who in 1851 paid a visit to Seneca
Falls, appeared in the bifurcated
dress, and Mrs. Bloomer published a
description of it. She and Elizabeth
Cady Stanton adopted the style and
advocated its peneral adoption.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn94052989/1894-12-31/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Amelia+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>AMELIA BLOOMER DEAD.
Passes Away Peacefully In Her
Home in Council Bluffs.
Council Bluffs, lowa, Dec. 30.— Mrs.
Amelia Bloomer, from whom the bloomer
costume, one of the first efforts toward
dress reform, was named, died at her home
in this city to-day.
Amelia Jenks Bloomer was born fn
Homer. N. V., May 27. 1818, her maiden
name being Jenks. In 1840 she married
Dexter C. Bloomer, a lawyer, and resided
in Seneca Fall?, N. Y. Here she. wrote
frequently on the enfranchisement of
women. On January 1, 1849, she issued
the first number of The Lily, a semi
monthly publication devoted to temper
ance and women's rights, which attained
quite a large circulation. She afterward
became associate editor of the Western
Home Journal, a literary weekly. She
lectured on women's rights and dress re
form at various cities and towns, and
adopted and publicly recommended a
sanitary dress for woman known as the
Bloomer costume. In later years she
withdrew entirely from public life.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86091038/1895-02-07/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Amelia+Bloomer</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MRS AMELIA BLOOMER
Death of the Woman Who First Made
Dress Reform Famous
Mrs Amelia Bloomer at one time
the most talked about woman in the
United States died on Deo 80 last
The use of the bloomer in bioyole riding
revived the story that she invented the
garment made famous by her name and
only recently she said that though she
had been among the firstto wear it she
had not invented it At no time in her
career though did she ride a bicycle
Amelia Jenks was born of New Eng
land parentage in Homer N Y May
27 1818 Six years later her parents
removed to Seneca Falls N Y and
there on April 15 1840 she was tnar
ned to Dexter 0 Bloomer Sho became
interested in the subjects of temperance
and womans rights and lectured on
them In 1849 after contributing ar
tides to various papers among them
The Waterbucket not the wastebasket
she started a semimonthly of her own
The Lily
At that time it was the fashion for
women to wear many skirts and the
style prescribed that a womans dress
should form the largest possible circum
ference Hoops were not yet introduced
and in order to attain a fashionable ex
pansiveness of skirt it was necessary to
wear so many petticoats that their
weight was extremely fatiguing On
this account Mrs Bloomer was anxious I
to adopt some sort of dress reform I
In 1851 the Seneca County Courier i
published an article written by a man
advocating the Turkish costume as a sensible
ible and becoming dress for women
rbe Courier man had been very severe
and sarcastio in his comments on the
womans rights question and Mrs
Jloomur in the next issue of The Lily
accused him of so far abandoning his
conservative views as to recommend
rousers for women and a good natured
controversy was carried on for some
time
timeht about this tim Mrs Elizabeth
ij tb Iin9 qJ t9t QtGorrJjBnii J q
r l v r
I
f
1
and a cousin of ilrs Elizabetfi Cady
Stanton went to visit in Seneca Falls
She wbre a costume which consisted of
a short skirt full trousers and an or
dinary bodice Mrs Bloomer looking
from her window and beholding the
queer toilet for the first time laughed
at it In a few days Mrs Elizabeth
Cady Stanton appeared in a short skirt
and trousers and in a week Mrs Bloom
er was persuaded to discard her ordinary
garments and put on the dress which
thenceforth bore her name Her first
reform costume was of figured silk and
the trousers which were gathered at the
ankle were of the same material
Nothing was more unexpected to Mrs
Bloomer than the sudden notoriety
which came to her Nothing was further
from her mind than the idea of setting
the fashion She did not wish to pose
as a dress reformer and had assumed
the peculiar costume merely for conven
ience But she calmly pursued her
work at the editorial desk and upon the
lecture platform always championing
tho cause of women and never referring
in any way to her costume
Under Presidents Taylor and Fillmore
Judgo Bloomer was postmaster of Sen
eca Falls and Mrs Bloomer was his
deputy In the performance of her du
ties in the postoffice Mrs Bloomer
found her short skirt convenient and
comfortable But the fame of her cos
tume spread rapidly and the circula
tion of Tho Lily jumped from a few
hundred to several thousand Mrs
Bloomer did not like the notoriety and
was often tempted to resume the heavy
burdenspme petticoats People traveled
miles to see her and cast curious glances
at her ankles Exaggerated and absurd
stories were circulated about her Ama
zonian form and masculine garments
Thus the first American dress reform
movement was started It was not ses
thetic it was not graceful and it was
finally lampooned out of existence
Mrs Bloomer abandoned the costume
to which she had given a name after
wearing it seven or eight years Why
she did so was never made public It
is known however that it was always
a source of anxiety lest she should be re
membered only because she once wore
an odd costume She was also very sen
sitive of the ridicule that costume had
caused to be heaped upon her husband
In 1853 Judgo and Mrs Bloomer re
moved to Mount Vernon O Mrs Bloom
er shortly afterward disposing of The
Lily In 1854 she was one of a commit
tee to memorialize tho legislature of
Ohio on a prohibitory liquor lawN In
1855 the Bloomers removed to Council
Bluffs where they have since resided
In 1850 Mrs Bloomer by invitation
addressed the legislature of Nebraska
on womans right to the ballot The ter
ritorial house of representatives shortly
afterward passed a bill giving women
the right to vote and in the council it
passed to a second reading but was
finally lost for want of time the limited
session drawing to a close Mrs Bloom
er took part in organizing the Iowa State
Suffrage association and was at one
time its president Poor health com
pelled her of late years to retire from
active work in the cause
In 1842 Mrs Bloomer joined the Protestant
estant Episcopal church of which she
remained a member all her life In 1890
her husband and she celebrated their
golden wedding</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024828/1895-03-09/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=bloomer+dress</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>What it a Bloomer Dress?
A lady gives the following explanation
''The bloomer dress is a pair of trousers
very baggy at the knees, abnormally
fall about the pistol pockets and consid
erably loose wbero yon strike a match.
The garment is cut decollete at the south
end, and ihe bottom ties around the
ankles or knees to keep the mice out.
You can't put it on over jour head as
j on do your corsets, but you sit on Ihe
flwrund pul it on jut bS you do your
stocklngE one foot in each coin pat tment.
You can easily tell which Is the right
side to have in front by the buttons
on the neck bind."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026853/1894-10-31/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=amelia+bloomer+costume</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The earliest woman'9 rights convention
was held at Seneca Falls, ElizabetkCady
Stanton, Frederick Douglass
ana Amelia Bloomer, of Bloomer costume
fame, being the originators.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84036287/1940-03-22/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=amelia+bloomer+costume</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Bloomers
yOU probably think "bloomers"
•t are called that because the word
sounds the way bloomers look. Well,
what would you think if they
called "jenkers"? That might have
been the word by which they
known today had not Miss Amelia
Jenks, for whom they were named,
been married to Dexter C. Bloomer.
Or had she married a man named
Smith they might
have been called
"smithereens," or
if she—well, with
all the names
there the possi
bilities are unlim
Mrs. Amelia
Jenks Bloomer of
mg Seneca Falls, N.
il Y., in 1849 start
ler ed a
were
ited.
woman's
magazine called
The Lily, and its
1 Ji

Mrs. Bloomer
purpose was to advocate temper
ance and women's rights. For pub
licity purposes, Mrs. Bloomer adopt
ed a costume consisting of a jacket
with close sleeves and a pair of
Turkish pantaloons secured around
the ankle by bands. Several of her
contemporary advocates of women's
rights wore the same costume and
these persons were known as
"Bloomerites" or just "Bloomers."
The campaign died out but the
pantaloon idea did not. A modified
form, shortened to gather just be
and became the bloomers as worn
today—or are they worn today?
least, Amelia Bloomer was the
spiration for bloomers as they are
remembered today.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88063294/1945-09-23/ed-1/?sp=71&amp;q=amelia+bloomer+costume</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>She insented bloomers,
although Amelia Hloomer introduced them as
a convenient, time-saving costume for women.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020355/1890-06-24/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=amelia+bloomer+costume</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE BLOOMER COSTUME. I
rhe Ladj WhoM Name ft Beam Denial
That She Introduced It.
The following letter from Mrs. Amelia
Bloomer, whose name became world
famous years ago in connection with
what was known as tho "Bloomer cos
tume," 4s printed in the Ladies'Homo
Journal, and has a keen dogrce of in
terest in that tho Mrs. Bloomer denies
tho credit of introducing tho costume in
America. Thislottor, recently written,
is now produced in print for tho first
timo: r
Council Bluffs, la. My Dear Sir:
I hardly know how to write about tho
"costume" associated with my name.
But I was not its inventor or originator,
as is so generally believed. i
In March, 1851, Elizabeth Smith Mil
ler, daughter of lion. Gerritt Smith, of
Potcrboro, N. Y., visited her cousin,
Elizabeth Cady Stanton, at Seneca Falls,
N. Y., which was then my home, and
whero I was publishing tho Lily, and
where Mrs. Stanton also resided. Mrs.
Miller came to us in a short skirt and
full Turkish trousers, a style of dress
sho had been wearing some two months.
Tho matter of woman's dress having
been just previously discussed in tho
Lily, Mrs. Miller's appearance led Mrs.
Stanton to at onco adopt tho stylo, and I
very soon followed, Mrs. Stanton intro
ducing it to tho Senoca Falls public two
or three days in advance of me. In tho i
next number of my paper following my
adoption of tho dress (April, 1851,) I
wrote an article announcing to my read
ers that I had donned the style to which
their attention had been cabled in previ
ous numbers. i
The Now York Tribune noticed nay
article, and made it known to its thou
sands of readers that I had donned a
short skirt and trousers, and from this
it went from paper to paper throughout
this country and countries abroad. I
found myself noticed and pictured in
many papors at home and abroad. I was
praised and censured, glorified and ridi
culed, until I stood in amazement at the
furor I had wrought by my pen whilo
sitting quietly in my little office at
home attending to my duties.
Suffice it that it was the press at
largo that got up all the excitement and
that namod tho dress. I never called it
the "Bloomer Costumcv" With mo it
was always tho short dress and trousers. I
It consisted of a skirt shortened to a
few inches below the knees and the
substitution of trousers made of the
same material as tho dress. In othor
rr?pects, the dress was the same as
worn by all women. At the outsot tho
trousers wero full and baggy, but we
improved upon them by making thorn
narrower and gathered at tho anklo,
and finally by making entirely plain
and straight, falling to tho shoe liko
tho trousers of men.
nVv .a- r iv !?i- n
xu nuni?j uxm-'uii, x tnink ido style was
adopted abroad, but not largoly, or, for 1
that matter, at home. There were in
dividuals hero and there who gladly
threw off tho burden of heavy skirts
and adopted the short ones, but soon
both press and people turned upon it
their ridicule and censure, and women
had not tho strength of princinlo to
witnstana the criticism, ana so returned
to their dragging skirts. For myself, I
wore the short dress and no othor, at
home and everywhere, for six or
sevon yoars, long after Mrs. Stan
ton, Lucy Stone and others had aban
doned it. Lucy Stone wore the dress
soveral yoars, traveled and lectured in
it. and was /narried in it, I think. Nono
of us over lectured on tho dress ques
tion, or in any way introduced it into
our lectures. Wo only wore it becauso
we found it comfortable, convenient,
safo and tidy?with no thought of intro
ducing a fashion, but with tho wish that
overy woman would throw off tho bur
den of clothos that was dragging her
life out.
This dress question has been of second
ary Importance with mo, and it is not
for that I wish to bo remembered. As
you will seo from what I have written
above, a wrong impression prevails in
regard to my part in that matter. I
was not its originator. 1 adopted tho
stylo and mado it known to the public.
The press did thorost.
I am not lecturing at all theso last
few years. A throat difficulty and my
seventy years have compelled ino to ro
tire from active participation in works
Tor tho advancement of woman.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99067997/1889-08-30/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=amelia+bloomer+costume</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>LADIES IN TROUSERS.
THE KUXIJIKK I»KI:SS KKIORIH OF
VOliTV YKAKS A»i«.
A» Ifof'orni Mnveme.it 11 W#« Not
S«irrps. IMII It Caused Seiixntioti i:i
Its 1
a.v Mrs. Mourner Is Still Living.
1«1 I (rossos Nou-a-Ii«.vs Like Othii
WollK'll.
AMKT.IA m.ooMKH. pleasant street can
read the name. Bloomer.
A few stone steps that ascend a little
grassv terrace, and two or three wooden
steps that rise to a vino covered veranda,
lead to the gold--lettered door-plate, which
most hospitably beckons strangers to enter
the wide hall every time the brown front
door is open. In the wide hall there are
two large portraits, one ot Miss Susan
Anthony and tlie other cf Mrs. Elizabeth
Cady .Stanton. From the hall a door open
into a Jow-cvi!ed. spacious drawing room
where then' arc sunnv windows that look
out upon tlie vine-covered veranda and the
little grassy terrace. Books, photographs,
and valuable souvenirs o£ the interesting
period when the door-plate was new and
the name upon it famous are s.atteied
Hhont 11juiTt tnMos mid cubinets. BoyoiiQ
the drawing room the half-drawn portieres
afford a glimpse of a library—such a cozy,
home-like room, with an open desk, an
easy chair or two, and a sewing basket,
placed in close proximity to one another.
A small, daintily formed woman cor
dially greets the stranger, whom tlie
si|iiare, gold-lettered plate has beckoned
into the house. She has a face tuat is
striking in its serene and gentle expres
sion. Soft, wavy gray hair is parted above
a broad, low brow, and a pair of earnest
ej-es look through gold-bowed spectacles.
There is nothing rugged or particularly
strong in the delicate features of th" face,
which is 1 eautiful with the touch of ad
vancing years. And her dress?—once
every one was interested in Mrs. Bloomer's
dress.
Nowadays Mrs. Bloomc-r's dres ilill'ers
in no important detail from thnl of any
other perfectly attired woman, and the
gown that she wears fits well it is plaited
and gathered and draped alter the latest
fashions. No one would ever believe that
Mrs. Bloomer was years ago heralded,
much against her wishes, as the great
dress reformer. It was all an accident
that her name became associated with ilie
short,-skirted costumes, and the story of
the dress reform movement that took
place in the 'oO's is most interesting,"e«iie
cially at a time when th-' Jenness-Milier
models are being so generally adopted.
In January, 184!), there was a temper
ance paper started by a society of ladies at
Seneca Falls, N. Y. The paper was called
the Lily, and Mrs. Amelia Bloimer be
came its editor. After the third number
Mrs. Bloomer assumed entire co itrol of
the paper editorially and fmancidly and
she began to be interested in the voman's
rights question, which was then first dis
cussed. In 1853 there appeared in the
Seneca County Courier a long eomnuniea
tion from some one who advocated a
change in woman's dress, and the Turkish
costume was suggested as both sens ble and
bocoming. Now the editor of the Seneca
County County Courier had seen fit to
frequently and ironically review the
woman's rigljts question, so Mrs.
Bloomer took advantage of ma
terial for a bantering editorial.
In the next issue of the Lily Mrs. Bloonfer
said that the Courier man had so far
abandoned his conservative views abciit
women that he actually recommended
trousers to them. She furthermore enum
erated various instances under which trous
ers seemed absolutely indispensable to
women. The Courier, in replying to the
editorial in the Lily, was deeply pained to
see Mrs. Bloomer treat a matter of such
grave importance with so much levity.
While the Courier was trying to thus
trample upon the Lily, Mrs. Elizabeth
Smith Miller, a daughter of the Hon.
Gerritt Smith and a sister of Mrs.
Elizabeth Cady Stanton, went to visit 111
Seneca Falls, and sho wore a costume
which astonished all the good people of
the town. It consisted of full trousers, a
short skirt, and an ordinary bodice. When
Mrs. Bloomer first saw Mrs. Miller go by,
attired in the strange garments, she
turned away from the window and laughed,
little dreaming that her own name would
one day be inextricably connected with
the costume that so much amused her. In
a few days Mrs. Elizabeth Cady Stanton
adopted the short skirt and trousers, and
Mrs. Bloomer, as one of the leaders of the
movement toward the advancement of
women, was straightway persuaded to
have one of the new costumes made. In
another week Mrs. Bloomer put off her
ordinary clothes and put on the dress that
thenceforth bore her name.
In 1852 it was the fashion for women to
wear a great number of skirts. In order
to be stylish, dressess had to stand out and
form the largest possible circumference.
Hoop skirts were not yet worn, and women
were accustomed to put on two or three
quilted and as many starched skirts, the
latter having been carefully dried over
barrels. The weight of the skirts was ex
tremely fatiguing, and the great mass of
women recognized the injurious effect of
such a fashion. Mrs. Bloomer's first re
form dress was of figured silk, and the
trousers, which were gathered at the
ankles, were of the same soft material.
Mrs. Stanton's new dress was of stouter
stuff, and consisted of a full suit of black
broadcloth with spring-bottom trousers.
Of course, the subject of dress was men
tioned in the Lily, which had a large cir
culation. The mails
immediately brought
hundreds of letters
from women who felt
the burdens and re
straints of the pre
vailing style of dress.
Many adopted the
short.skirts and trous
ers, but only to be
laughed out of them
and, although Mrs.
Bloomer wore the cos
tume during the eight
years that she was be
fore the public, only
a small portion of
women even tried the
odd dress. Mrs. Stan
ton adhered to it two
years, and thee, yield
ed to the protests of
husband and friends
and abandoned, it.
A BOSTON LADY IN
18j2.
The nr.st paper to notice tne new garb
assumed by tho few progressive women of
that time was the New York Tribune,
which was then under the management of
Horace (ireeley, and in a few weeks everv
paper in the I nited States devoted more
ore less space to what they chose to call
the Blooiiur costume "v the papers
msm
v-
in Coun­
cil Bluffs, says
the Oinaha Re
publican, there is
a square, gold-letter
ed door-plate. It lias
lieen polished thirty
years or more, and
"the gold letters are
not so distinct as they
used to be, yet any
one passing along the
commended what seemed to be a laudable
cll'ort to break away from senseless and
unhcalthful fashions in woman's dress, but
the tone of the press soon changed. Bloom
erism was ridiculed and misrepresented
everywhere.
'Nothing was more unexpected than the
sudden notoriety that cany to Mrs.
Bloomer. She did not dream of making
such a furor when she assumed a style of
dress wh ch ssemed lietter adapted to the
needs of a busy woinon than the heavy
skirted, uncomfortable gowns tlvn in
vogue. She never intended to set tho
fashion, and nothing could have bee.. :,iore
distasteful to her than the widespread com
ment which the short skirt and trousers
excited. But once having put 011 the re
form costume, Mrs. Bloomer would not be
laughed out of it. She calmly pursued he*
chosen work at her editorial desk and upon
the lecture platform. While editing the
Lily she made fraquent lecture urs
through the North and South, speaking
upon the two subjects dearest to her—tem
perance and woman suffrage. Although
she lecttfred in the short skirts and
trousers she did not in any way
allude to her dress, for she neither desired
nor attempted to be a dress reformer. She
wore the costume because it suited her
needs as editor, lecturer, and busimss
woman. Mrs. Hloomer's fame was ex
tremely unpleasant to her. People
traveled miles to see her, and the atten
tion that her clothes attracted to her was
often so distasteful that she was tempted
to return to the nuiltod petticoats and
starch, skirts. Whenever she finished a
lecture people crowded arojund the plat
form and cast surreptitious glanc. at her
ankles. All sorts of absurd stories were
circulated about her appearance, and tho
popular opinion was expressed by a
woman who said to her: "You're not at
all what 1 expected to see. I thought you
were a coarse, Amazonian woman."
la England much curiosity was shown
reg.Yding tiie woman's rights movement,
and Voou after tue first furor over the
-—V
/W.
FACSIMILE OF OXE OF
THE FIRST REFOIUI
COSTUMES.
A FASIUOXAIU.K
DRESS IX 1
short skirts and trousers a large picture of
Mrs. Bloomer appeared in th'j London
Illustrated News.
In time the Lily grew and flourished and
became a semi-monthly publication. But'
one day Mrs. Bloomer was compelled to
dispose of her paper. Mr. Bloomer hail
become affected with the Western fever,
and so the Lily was sold to Miss Mary
Birdsall of Richmond, Ind. The cause o£!
woman's rights had begun to be recog
nized in the years that the Lily so bravely,
championed the equal privileges of the
sexes, and many women had joine the
little group who first dared to suggest that
woman's sphere was almost as broad as
that of man. When the Lily was first
published there were onty three avenues of
employment open to women—teaching,
sewing, and housework—and every woman
who to-day occupies a position in a pro
fession or a business is indebted to the few
women who first had courage enough to
agitate the subject of woman's rights.
Mr. and Mrs. Bloomer came west to
their new home in Council Bluffs, and the
little woman who so astonished tlie world
by her independence retired from public
life. In January, lS.'o, the second Ter
ritorial Legislature of Nebraska invited
Mrs. Bloomer to deliver a lecture on
woman's rights in the hall of the House of
representatives at Omaha, and she spoke
with so much effect that a newspaper cor
respondent gave her the highest praise in
his power. He said: "A man could not
have beaten it.''
Such is the history of tho rise and fall
of the Bloomer costume, a dress-reform
movement that created more talk than has
any similar movement in this country.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-clara-h-barton</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025287/1881-05-22/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Miss Clara
Barton, prominently identified with sanitary
and hospital work during the civil war and
conspicuous during the Fninoo-Prus.-Un war,
as one of the red cross representatives,
read a piper showing the scope and efficiency
of the Red Cross societies in countries where
tbe order is recognized by government and ac
corded the powers and privileges which are
asked for it in the United States.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86064205/1887-08-10/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MISS UAKTONS AriOINTMKXT
Washington Aug Miss Clara
Barton president of the American
National Association of the Red Cross
and Dr J B Hubbell general agent and
secretary of the association have been
appointed by President CI vjlan dele
gates to represent the United States at
the fourth international conference of the
attend the Geneva conference in 1 4
the lirst international conference in
Red Cross to be held at the court of the
Grand Duke and Duchess of Baden
which opens at Cirlfiuhe Germany Sep
tember 22 This will be Miss Bartons
second errand to Europe as a Rd Cross
representative from this countrv having
which the United States was represented</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99021999/1889-06-06/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Clara Barton of Washington the origi
nator of the well-known Keel Cross corps nr-
rived hero this morning nnd will nt once assume
sumo charge of all the female relief corps.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1896-01-23/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MISS HARTOrf OFF FOR ARMENIA
With the Red Coa Fine FlantlnB from
the New Tort Mizzen Track
Miss Clara Barton President of the American
Tied Cross Society who Is going to try to take
charge of the distribution of American dona
tions for the relief of sufferers in Armenia ar
rived In this city nt 7 oclock yesterday morn
log from Washington She was met nt tho
station by a committee from the New York Red
Cross and escorted t Delmonlcos where n fare
well breakfast was given In her honor Mrs
Charles C Raymond President of the New
York Red Cross presided Those present were
tin P C Dennis Mrs C II H Cottrell the
Hon George C Barrett Gen and Mrs Olorov
icky Mr and Mrs Stephen E Iarton Miss
Myotls Barton Dr O Steger Mrs M W
Kraus Dr A tonne Lessor Medical Director
of the New York Red Cross and the other
members of the party who will accompany
itlss Barton on her foreign mission These are
George H Pullman financial agent Dr J I
Hubbell field surgeon Ernest Mason linguist
and Miss Lucy Graves secretary toMlss Barton
Mrs Raymond made a speech wishing Miss
Barton the successful accomplishment of the
object of her journey and a safe and quick re
turn Miss I Barton replied briefly and an
nounced her Intention of sending nt once to
this country for A competent corps of nurses
provided she Is l admitted to Armenia
After the breakfast the entire party left for
the American line pier to see Miss Barton safely
aboard the New York on which she suited at 11
clock Several newspaper men were awaiting
ber and In reply to their questions she said
I do not know that the Sublime Porte has
announced to the Turkish Minister at WashliiR
ton fund Its opposition t the distribution of this
tnd
fundDo
Do you mean to say then that you dont
believe that such announcement has been
made
made1s Barton replied laughingly I dont say
that You can say It If you want to I have no
definite plans I shall mature my plans ns I become
como more thoroughly acquainted with tho oh
tacles to be overcome I was asked to do this
work because her couldnt get any one else to
do II I am simply the agent for carrying out 0
great work I do not know the amount of tho
relief fund I am going to Armenia to care for
he sick and feed the hungry There Is no
bravado In my going abroad I am a simple
womanbent on ahumnno and difficult mission
Miss Barton expects to arrive In Constantino
ple In I about twentyone days Including short
stays nt nnl an and ileneva Immedi I
ately upon her arrival sue will confer with Min
sterTerrell l with 0 view to bringing the lion
poses ot her mission before the Sultan amid
securing the neeesarv permission for carrying
nits work I vvas said ypstenlay by those in
A position to know that Miss liarton now nas
50000 at her disposal and that moro will bo
forthcoming as soon as the attitude or the
Turkish Government toward tho movement becomes
comes settled
eelte
Many telegrams and floral tributes awaited
Hiss Barton aboard the New York One of the
alter came from the Armenians of this city As I
the big liner moved out into tho stream the tai
of the Red Cross Society floated at the inlzzen
truck nnd Capt Orant said that It should stay
here nil the way across the ocean
Before leaving Washington Miss Barton had
an Interview with Cardinal Sntolll who gave
her n letter to the Oran Patrlnrch ni Constantinople

Inoplc who U I said to be quite Intimate with I
the Sultan Miss Barton hopes that the letter
will prove a valuable means of securing recog
nition by the ulan
WARIIISOTOX Inn 2The following Is the
official announcement of the Red Cross on the
lepnrturoof Miss Clara Burton and a part of 1
he staff today for Europe
In accordance with its undcrntnndlnc with the Na
tional Armenian lUllef Committee of Xew York n1 I
the Armenian Relief romialttees of llmtoti arid Wor
ester the American National lied Cross starts toslny
for Turkey 10 lnv tlmti on the spot and ileteniilan
whether or not II will he able to distribute loC r
monu the nufTerera from famine want and fclcLiiem
BOc
in different sections of Turkey
As we never solicit funds for our work the above
named Armenian Hellef Committee fat whits soil
citation the Hoc Cross han responnedl have undi
taken the ralsnic of funds and supplies which will I
utilized b us
In ease It is I found Impracticable orlmposslhlefor
U is to adequately distribute the relief we will jots is I
he several cnmmtttfcs and other existing tiirenc let I
wii If Used 00 that all contributors may be mcureit I
hat motley and material given by them wilt reach
the sufferers
Thn lied Cross will be In constant communication
with these committees I who will I inuke renortfi lo tho
public I from tint to time of the progress or mir ol
In itt mean lime all funds should IMJ sent In MrKtirft
Irow n Pro I Co New York Ilo lnn and I Plilladt1
phis lo lip placed to mite credit of Cite Armenian relief
fund or to inn American I National lied Crns
CUIIA IURTOS President Am a Keel Cross
JTILL THE KULTAX ADMIT HER I
Krrbrt to Opt n Permit for the Red Cross
Hnclety to Enter Anntolln
CONSTANTINOPLE Jan 22 Minister Terrell 1
rays that he does not desire to make any state
ment In regard 10 the prohnblllty of thin Sultan
consenting to Miss Clara Bartons I proposed dis
tribution of relief among tint Armenians in
Asia Minor I Is learned from other sources
that Mr rell Is making earnest efforts both
at the palace anti the Porte tn secure tho ad 1
mission of tho lied Cross Society Into Aimtollu
with full permission to supply the needs ot thu
tarvlng Armenians</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1899-01-15/ed-1/?sp=17&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CLARA BARTON DESCRIBES THE RED CROSS WORK IN CUBA
In Her Forthcoming Book She Will Tell Ail About the Horrors of the Cuban Campaign as She and Her Assistants Saw It, and Wall Score the War Department.
IN her forthcoming book on the history of the Red Cross So
ciety, a review of whose preliminary chapters has already ap
peared in the New York Sunday Herald, Miss Clara Barton will
give to the world a thrilling— almost a grewsome— narrative
of official mismanagement. Through the courtesy of the pub
lishers the advance sheets of those newer portions of the work
that deal with the Cuban campaign are here reviewed. The state
ments are Miss Barton's, and will appear over her own name in
the volume to be issued next month.
It must remain for the War Investigation Commission to lay
the blame for the shameful mismanagement she describes on the
proper shoulders. Every candid reader will rise from the perusal
of the book with the fixed impression that had it nut been for the
aid cheerfully extended by the Red Cross and grudgingly accepted
by the military authorities, the loss of life and health at Siboney
and Santiago would have been well nigh unparalleled in the history
of modern warfare.
The publishers of the book are the American National Red
Cross at Washington, D. C.
IN reviewing Miss Barton's forth
coming book I must necessarily
pass over much that is Interesting
about the beginning of the Red
18 campaign in Cuba and the
official stumbling blocks placed in the
society's way, and come down to the
.Bltuatij-in just previous to the destruc
tion of the Maine. At this time Miss
■Barton was already well established in
r.Cuba, and was dispensing relief at
■-Ceno, a suburb &lt;.f Havana.
Explosion of the Maine.
It. was before this good work was well
In-hand that the explosion of the Maine
■'occurred. Miss Barton describes how;
on th/&gt; memorable February 15. the
clerical work to be dono was so heavy
..that it kept herself and Mr. Elwell, her
.'lnterpreter and secretary, busy at
tjieir writing table until late at nicht.
"The house had grown still, the
'ibises' on the streets were dying away,
..'When suddenly the table shook from
xinder -our hands, the great glass door
on the veranda, facing the
i-^a, flew open; everything in the room
was In motion or out of place, the
deadening roar of such a buret of
thunder as, perhaps, one never heard
lpefore, and off to the right, out over
the bay, the air waa filled .-with a blaze
THE CALL Sunday Edition.
of light,' and this, in turn, filled witn
black specks like huge epeters flying
in all directions.
"Then it faded away. The bells ran*,
the whistles blew and voices In the
street were heard for a moment. Then
all was quiet again. I supposed it to
be the bursting of some mammoth mor
tar or explosion of some magazine. A
few hours later came the terrible news
of the Maine."
Some forty of the wounded were
brought ashore and placed in the Span
ish hospital of San Ambrosio. All the
jni'mbers of the Red -ross hurried to
th( ir relief.

Upon the advice of the Consul Gen
eral at Havana the lied Cross retired
when the President recalled all Ameri
cans home. The day before they ]*-f t
Cuba the Archbishop of Havana pub
licly blessed the Lee Orphanage in the
presence of a large crowd. In the eyes
Of nil Catholics, Cuban and Spanish
alike, this blessing was a symbol of
protection by the church and a warrant
of success. Hence Miss Barton was not
surprised to lea-rn several months after
the war had begun that the Spanish
authorities had not only taken the most
scrupulous care of the hospital, but
had also placed a guard around her
former private residence.
Return to Key Weet.
On April 11, 1898, Miss Barton and her
staff! boarded the ship Olivette and after
a great deal of discomfort caused by
overcrowding of passengt s and stormy
weather, reached Tampa, Fla., two daya
later. Leaving the rest of the party at
Tampa, Miss Barton proceeded to
Washington with Drs. Hubbell and
Egan. The Red Cross agents left in
Florida found work enoug-h to hand in
looking after the 1500 Cuban refugees In
Tampa and the 800 or 900 in Key West.
These people were almost entirely de
pendent for a period of some seven
months upon the good offices of the Red
Cross agents.
In the meantime Miss Barton, in
Washington, also had her hands full.
Early in April it had been decided by
the Cuban Relief Committee in New
York to charter a steamer in that port,
load her with supplies and send her
to different ports in Cuba, where her
cargo could be unloaded in such quanti
ties as might be required.
The steamer Btate of Texas was ac
cordingly selected. Notwithstanding the
departure of the Red Cross party from
Havana and the subsequent declaration
of war with Spain the preparations
were kept up and the steamer was load
ed with a cargo embracing a fine as
sortment of necessaries and delicacies,
medicine and other hospital stores. She
arrived at Key West on April 28, and
was met by Miss Barton, who had come
down from Washington, and all the
Red Cross assistants who had been left
in Tampa.
Key West at that time was a very
busy place, the harbor being filled with
naval vessels which came in daily from
the Cuban blockade squadron for coal
and provisions. There was scarecly
a day that some accident did not hap
pen to sailor or workman. The Red
Cross doctors were at all times in de
mand. In order to keep every one in
the best preparation for possible con
tingencies those on board the State of
Texas were instructed and drilled in
the various phases of their particular
work, and at all times of the day the
Red Cross boat, with its well known
flag floating, could be seen going from
one transport to another on Its errand
of mercy.
Prisoners Left to Starve.
There were other charities which
clamored for the attention of the Red
Crocs officials. Scarcely a day passed
that Borne of the blockading squadron
did not bring into Key West from one
to three captured prizes— ships, schoon
ers, steamers or fishing smacks. With
in a couple of weeks after the declara
tion of war there were between thirty
and forty of these boats lying at an
chor in the harbor with their crews
aboard under guard. Somehow it was
forgotten these poor foreigners must
eat to live! Or perhaps somebody
thought that somebody else was re
sponsible for this very important mat
ter.
At all events, when the small amount
of provisions aboard the boats at the
time of capture had been exhausted,
calls were made on the United States
Marshal for additional food. Having
no contingent fund upon which to draw,
and knowing the quantities of red tape
that must be unraveled before he could
SAN FRANCISCO, SUNDAY, JANUARY 15, 1899.
secure any relief, the Marshal came
to Miss Barton with his troubles. That
good lady reassured him by promising
to provide for all the prisoners until
such time as he could Ret his petition
through the circumlocution office.' Sev
eral boatloads of provisions were hasti
ly gathered and taken in tow by a
steam launch, which landed them
alongside of each prize.
Miss Barton visited every boat in per
son, learned the wants of the crews
through an Interpreter, and not only
supplied all needed foods, but ar
ranged to take all letters and forward
them to their destination through the
intermediary offices of the Red Cross at
Portugal.
Could Not Reach Reconcentrados.
On.' June 20, everything being in read-*
mess, and no disapproval having been
elicited from the Navy Department, it
was decided to sail and find Sampson's
fleet near Santiago de Cuba, Here it
was generally believed that General
Shafter would try to effect a landing.
On the 25th the State of Texas arrived
off Morro. Castle, at the entrance of
Santiago Bay. The Spanish flag was
flying over the land fortifications and
Sampson's fleet was stationed in the
adjacent waters.
Miss Barton sent a 'representative
aboard I the flagship New York asking
Rear Admiral Sampson for instructions.
Word was returned that General Sh.af
ter's army had disembarked at Bai
quiri, a point about twelve miles east
if Morro Castle. The admiral advised
Miss Barton to take her ship to Guan
tanamo.Bay, where she would find good
anchorage and calm water, and where
she would be able to learn more of
ivhat was taking v place on land, as
there was constant communication
from there with the invading army.
rho Texas accordingly drew away and
irrived that evening at Playa del Este,
lust inside the mouth of Guantanamo
F3ay and some forty miles from Santi
igo.
Here two reporters from New York
japers called. on Miss; Barton, inform
ng her that' they had Just come in
Crom Siboney, where there was great
leed of supplies and medical aid. They
old how, many of the wounded in the
Ight between the Rough Riders and the
Spaniards, on the previous Friday, had
iust been brought in and were suffer
ng from lack of everything in the way
if comfort and conveniences. The
steamer was at once headed westward
md started to the scene of suffering,
which she reached at 8 o'clock.
A party of doctors accomplished a
difficult 'landing' in an open boat and
found their way to the army hospital.
This was a rough wooden building
which had evidently been used for a
store and warehouse in more peaceful
times. The surgeon in charge, Major
Havard, stepped forward to greet the
visitors, who formally offered him. in
the name of Clara Barton and the Red
Cross, the personal; services of all their
doctors and nurses and any of their
supplies that might be needed. These
were courteously refused. Major Hav
ard thought that .he and his assistants
would be able to take care of all the
3ick and wounded, and, as for supplies,
lie knew that there was an abundance
of them on the transports, which he
hoped would be landed next day.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1900-09-17/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CLARA BARTON
IN GALVESTON
Red Cross President Horrified at the Awful
ScenesPraise for the World
ffUI t TT Ftltfil well i
tUIVBSfiX nnpr IMU tarn
Pnrlili Iriiirlini a qv Nllon Hnl
Irati rimlPit wit hoe rhnllP n the
iippllf ihi ti e print MrwnrilNl h
all Th Worlil Miff irMnf Attired
lyre till morIn will her urt Hhr
PO reNvel I MAIOr Jonni and wtlh
nlm umln K nmr of inni tlnn nl the
city
tiro llnrlon haA ben the rfrlpliit nf
ollltUI ittrntlon lnr lifmrrlvil H
llninlon Miir ilrarhner woe III
having nurciunli In Ihr trin of eA
crrell work hot ctlnir Mnyor I I
Taffy Ant in oflklnl rnfilliiltli rrprr
imllnr the muiuclpiilll nut tun rfikf
noelttlri to fret her nl the IliiUliln
Homo AAA named Mr IMrr Chilintri
tu iron Mill lUrton And ultft t tai
vmlon
Mar ntrton MJd to Thf World eorr
tion lent who unterrtt Ultrilon with
her patlr What I hate iwn Pled
what I hA t Urn ltd to unilclpilit from
the Tf roporli It II mirvfllnni in
twhnld how the city hu lUtvUrl the
dlllrr Thin li in linmtiu ninmini
of work to be don her The up
pile i that arrived htte on Thr World I
rlltt tralnn An Jut whet ire nr dil
And UAJnr Jonn wan ddlihlnl III hcnr
thai a Nw York firm mti IIrlloIIIIK
Ilvi IhoUMtid iilKini of dlnlnfrctlnK
iluli on a World rtlltf Itlill now epeMI
Inr toward this city
nom what I iw In lloutton and
hen todny I Thank tod that I hn
jn ptnnlllf to come to the tnicu
or thai Afflicted people
lln lUrlon and hr tuff whit Arc
lout aitabllalilni a r lltf depot al over
tof the dlitrlbuUim uf Th Viirlila rr
Itf tiljipllaa</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1902-08-06/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CLARA BARTON HOME FROM
RTTSSIA TELLS OF THE CZAR
e
I Great White Monarch
Rcfus vf to Let Bene
facto of the Worlds
Sold crs Bow to Kiss
i His Tand but Shook
Hers Instead
I
Miss Clara Barton the Pre ucnt of
the American Red Cross frcreiy arrl d
In Hoboken today on the Hamburg
American liner Pennsylvania She had
been to the qulntehnlnl conference off
the International ned Cross Association
I t and was full of cnthuslaim about It On
the boat nlfo were Mrs Harriet Hubbard
Ayer and her daughter Miss Margaret
f
Ayer who has been flnlihlnc her mu
r sical education abroad
S 4 Fifty nations were represented said
Mlis Barton by the hundred delegates
to the conference I was treated with
suchgreat kindness that I can hardly
find words to express my appreciation
The Czar personally decorated me
with the highest order with which he
can honor any one not of royal blood a
decoration which he has bestowed upon
I
many of the crowned heads of Europe
I was entertained In the royal palsccn
of Russia and the Imperial railway
trains were placed at my dlaposal
CaRr Doa to Her Honor
B F TJIIln hart another Red Cross
delegate spoke up
When Miss Barton was presented to
the Czar he said she bent to kiss
I I the monarchs hand as Is the custom
but the great white Czar drew back and
f said No not you Miss Barton and
shook her hand Instead Her whole tour
through Russia was a triumphal Journey
for this worldpopular woman
I was very much Impressed sold
Miss Barton with the Czars earnest
ness for desiring universal peace and to
I
assuage the horrors of war
Standing on the pier this aged om
I an hale and hearty despite her Ions
i years of beneficent service looked as
hale and hearty as a woman half her
age She was the centre of a throne
of steamer friends eager to speak to
her once more before leaving
Wore Armenian Decoration
She wore a green dress and a green
and red plaid shawl clasped with her
Armenian decoration which she prizes
very highly</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045555/1904-03-26/ed-1/?sp=13&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>It may bo re
marked In passing that America was
not one of the original signatory pow
ers cither but It was through Clara
Barton ihe head of the American so
ciety In niter year that the victims of
natural calamities Biich ns earthquakes
and llooclc wero added as subjectH ot
Hell Cross work Incidentally Hnssla
was also concerned In this but ns a
recipient At tho time of tho great
Russian famine Miss Ilarlon under
this very provision organized mlpslon
of mercy that pained the undying grat
itude nf the Slav empire</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1904-05-15/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CLARA BARTON BARTON BARYON
RETIRING PRESIDENT OF RED CROSS CROSSMiss CROSSMiss CROSSMiss
Miss Barton for twentythree years was president of the society societyand societyand societyand
and gave to it the qualities of a vigoious and notable notablepersnaU notablepersnaUMrs personality personalityMrs personalityMrs
Mrs John A Logan chosen as vice president a year ye r2gO ago succeeds Miss MissBarton MissI MissBarton
I Barton as head of the Red Cross Society
HAS R SNtW NE HEA HEAl HEAD HEADMis l
1 1Ils
Mrs Ils Logan Log n Succeeds Miss MissClara MissClara
i Clara BartonEXECUTIVE Barton BartonEXECUTIVE DartonEXECUTIVE
EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE ACTS ACTSFormer ACTSFormer ACTSFormer
Former President PresicfentResignsVice Resigns ResignsVice Vice Presi Presii President
i dent d nt Is Chosen foFillVacanCY foFillVacanCYLetter to o Till 7ilf Vacancy VacancyLetter VacancyLetter
Letter and Memorial MemorialMiss MemorialMiss MemorialMiss

Miss Bartons Bart reslgnatlonpf r resignation slgno onpt of the presi presidency presidency presidency
dency dency of the American Amer cim lied Cross yes yesterday yestCrday es est
terday t rc ny andthe and andthoehctlon the election of Mrs John A ALogan ALogan j
Logan to the head he d of the society were werenot werenot j
not steps toward the reorganization of ofthe ofthe ofthe
the society on compromise lines sug suggested suggested suggested
gested by Gen JohnW John W Foster FpsterMrs F FosterMrs ster sterMrs
Mrs Logan denies denl s that she has had hadany hadany hadany
any official notification of the th Foster Fosterplan FosterpIAn Fosterplan
plan for reorganization which was laid laidj laldbetore laidbefore
j before the Red Cross Investigating com committee commlttee committee
mittee of which Senator Proctor Is Ischairman Ischairman ischairman
chairman The TheremonaWants remonstrants r monJtran1 who forced forcedthe torcedi forcedthe
i the investigation had nothing to to do with withthe withthee
i the advancement of Mrs Logan to the thepresidency thepresldenc thepresidency
presidency presldenc and say they will not sup support support
I port the society societywhile while It operates under underits underi underits
i its present constitution constltutlonand and bylaws bylawsConsequently bYlawsConsequently bylawsConsequently
Consequently the changes brought broughtabout broughtabout
I about In the organization yesterday by bythe bythe bythe
the Barton followers will have no effect ef effect
I fect on the controversy controe y between the two twofactions twoI twofactions
I factions of the tlffisoclcty society While Miss MissBarton MissJ MissBartonV
J Barton arton and her hersupporers supporters supprers allege that thatthey thatI thatthey
I they acted In the hope of restoring restoringharmony restoringharmcn restoringharmony
harmony harmcn it Is Intimated by the he remon remonstrants remonstrants rernonstrants
strants that the Barton faction brought broughtabout broughtaboutn broughtabout
about aboutn a change hang in tha th head hoadot of the Rod RodCross RodI RqdCross
I Cross in the hope of heading headlngoitf1rthor headlngoitf1rthori off further furtherInvestigation furthorinvestigation
i Investigation Im cstlgatlon of the finances ftnancesof of the socioty so soclety 50clety
clety V
Conference With Committee CommitteeImmediately CommitteeImmediately CommitteeImmediately
Immediately Immediately after Mrs frs Logan was
elected to the presidency of the organl organlzatlori organlzatIon organization
zatIon yesterday she held a conference conferencewith conC conferencewith renae renaewith
with the members of the executive ex c1tlve com committee aommlttce com committee
mittee Gen Nelson A Miles Eugene B BFlak BFisk BFisk
Fisk S S Hege and S W Y Briggs at atwhich ntwhich atwhich
which it was decided that a meeting of ofthe orthe ofthe
the full board of trustees shall be held heldon he holdon tl tlon
on May 2C 2 when the policy of the new newadministration newadministration newadministration
administration will be outlined It is issaid Issaid issaid
said that Miss Barton will win attend nttt nd that thatmeeting thatmeeting thatmeeting
meeting and transfer all the assets and andpapers andpI andpapers
papers pI tS of the society to Mrs Logan LoganA
A meeting Of the full society secI ty will also alsobe alsobe alsobe
be called for September 6 at which no noproxies noproxies noproxies
proxies will be b accepted The nnnounce announcement nnnouncerncnt nnnouncementthat
ment mentthat that proxies will not be beacccptod accepted la laespecially IJ3cspeclaJ1 isespecially
especially significant 1 as too tootJce free a use useqf UseQC useQf
qf them at tho annual meeting of the thesociety thesociety thesociety
society two years Qars ago provoked the thestorm thetorm thestorm
storm torm which whlC i1 caused the remonstrants remonstrantsto r monstrnntsto
to secede and force an Investigation of ofRed ofRed ofRed
Red Cross methods methodsWant methodsWant methodsWant
Want the Investigation InvestigationMiss InvcstigationMlss InvestigationMiss
Miss Mabel T Boardman and other otherremonstrants othorlemonstrants othertemonstrants
remonstrants who were wer sfeon tico1l last st night nightsay night3ay nightsay
say they will not agree to any compro compromise compromise compromise
mise measure which provides pr ldestor for a less lessthorough lessthorough lessthorough
thorough reorganization than thanth that t sug suggested suggested 5uggested
gested by Gen John W Foster Ac According 4ccording According
cording to his plan the society would wouldhave wouldhavc wouldhave
have a governing board boar of twelve tolv mem members membC1rs mombers
bers four fouro of whom would be named by byPresident byPresident byPresident
President Roosevelt Roos eltf four by Miss Bar Bartons BartOJ1S Bartops
tons supporters supporters and four by the reraon reraonstranjs re remonstrnnts on onstran
stranjs stranjsIn stran strnntsIn s sIn
In the t e presence pr sonce of tho executive com committee COnmlttee conltnittee
mittee of ot the thQROd Rod Cross Cross Miss Barton Barton</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1904-05-20/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Clara+Barton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MAKES MAKESANSER MAKESANSERS MAKESANSERTO ANSWER ANSWERTO S
TO REMONSTRANTS REMONSTRANTSlriend
Friend of Miss liss Barton Pre Prepares Prc1areS Prepares
pares 1areS Statement StatementWELL StntpluelltWELL State1llentWELL
WELL QUALIFIED TO SPEAK SPEAKJaact SPEAKJanet SPEAKJanet
Janet Jennings for Twenty Years As Associated Ass Asdated
sociated s dated atcd in the Work With WithMiss With3liss ith ithMiss
Miss Barton BartonFrom BartonFrom BartonFrom
From the inception of the move on onthe onthe onthe
the part of the remonstrants in tho thoAmerican thoAmerican theAmerican
American American Red Cross Society Soclel to effect a acomplete acomplete acomplete
complete reorganization of that body bodyClara bodyClara bodyClara
Clara Barton tho executive and chief chieffigure chloffigure chieffigure
figure of tho Institution has steadfastly steadfastlyrefused steadfastlyreCused stendfaatlyrefu
refused refu ed to mako any public statement statementconcerning alatementneernlng atatementcencerning
concerning neernlng It ItNow itNow L Low
Now ow that Miss Barton has resigned resignedhowever resIgnedhowever resignedhowever
however one of her associates AS oclates in the thework thoark thework
work ark for the past twenty years e rs has hasprepared hasJJrepnrld hasprepared
prepared an answer to the charges of ofthe oftht ofth
the th remonstrants That friend Is IsJanet IsJmet IsJanet
Janet Jennings a coworker in the Red RedCross RedCr08S RedCross
Cross with Miss Barton and her aide in inCuba InCuba inCuba
Cuba Her statement is as follows followsFor followsFor followsFor
For some years eArs Miss Barton as well wellknown wellknown ell ellknown
known desired to retire from the presi presidency pres presidency 1 1tncy
dency tncy of the Red Cross Sho had plans plansfor plansCer plansicr
for work that she believed would be bemore bemore bemere
more valuable to the cause than her herservice herrvlcc herservice
service rvlcc as president Again and again againduring againdurllg againduring
during tho past two years she has been beenheld beenhe1t beenheld
held resolutely back h ck by b friends who re refused refusro refused
fused to believe that her resignation resignationwould 1esignatIonwould oslgnaUonwould
would relieve the society soclet from further furtherdifferences turtherasrrertnces furtherdifferences
differences which of late have been In Ineffect Ineffect ineIeet
effect a personal attack on the president presidentof
of the Red Cross CrossMiss CrossMiss CrossMiss
Miss Bartons friends declared they theywould th theywould y ywould
would stand pat to the bitter end or orgo orgo orgo
go out with her She would not permit permitthem permitthem permitthem
them to do do cither The vice president presidentshe presidentshe presidentshe
she said as provided for in the bylaws bylawsshould b3lawsshould bylawsshould
should take her place and the organiza organization organization organization
tion would remain Intact until the an annual annual annual
nual meetinsr meeUn next January JanuRr when of officers otficers offleers
ficers will be elected The organization organizationshould organizationshould organizationshould
should not suffer another day from a apersecution n1eISecutlon apersecution
persecution directed at her through the thesociety thesodet thesociety
society sodet If the methods adopted by bythose b3tho bythose
those tho seeking to break up the Red Cross Crossare CrOSare Cressare
are to go on then the organization organizationshould organizationshould organizationshould
should be saved and she would stand standout standout standout
out alone In the open and give them a aclear aclear aclear
clear field before bbfore the American people peopleMiss peopltMias peopleMiss
Miss Barton had her way The vice vicepresident vicepresident Ice Icepresident
president became the acting president presidentthe presidentthe presidentthe
the moment Miss Bartons resignation resignationwas re Jgnatlon JgnatlonWas
was accepted by the executive commit committee committee committee
tee which alone had the power to accept acceptit
it as in the absence of a session of the theboard theboard theboard
board of trustees the executive com committee commltteehas cornrnittec
mittee mltteehas has all the powers of the full fullboard tullboard fullboard
board
What Will Miss Barton Do DoAnd DoAnd DoAnd
And now what will the expresident of ofthe ofthe orthe
the American National Red Cross do doWhat dohat doWhat
What hat will she not do She will never nevermake nevermake nevermake
make any an reply to her friend the ene enemy enemy onemy
my She will will never make any an defense defenseof defenseof defenseof
of her life to the American people who whohave whohae whohare
have never asked it and never desired do lred it itShe ItShe itShe
She will hold to her first decision never neverto neverto neverto
to be Interviewed on the events of ofthe ofthe ofthe
the past two years though appreciative appreciativeand
and grateful for every kind word in the thepress thepress thepress
press Nobody Nobod has ever heard her speak speaka
a retaliatory word wordno no criticism crltlclsmonly crltlclsmonlysilence criticismonlysilence only onlysilence
silence and suffering in agony of mind mindsuch mtncIsuch mindsuch
such as an oversensitive rotlcont proud proudnature proul1nllture proudnature
nature Is capable of ofLet ofLet ofLet
Let us hope that this cessation CC84atlonthe CC84atlonthefirst cessationthefirst the thefirst
first In twentyfive years yearswill ear8wlJl will enable enableher enableher enableher
her to leave to the world some record recordof rocordof recordof
of a 3 most remarkable life Who so sowell sowelJ sowell
well as herself could give this as a alast a1Mt aIaRt
last word ord to the people and the country countryshe oountryshe countryshe
she has so Iqng and faithfully served servedIt BenedIt servedIt
It will be interesting on the other otherhand otherhand otherhand
hand to know what the Remonstrants Remonstrantswill Remonstrantswill Remonstrantswill
will do Will 111 they th go on aTkl a1 d continue continuethe contlnuthe continuethe
the persecution pers uUan of Clara Baron through throughthe throughthe throughthe
the few short years that may be left leftto leftto leftto
to her Or will they now call a halt haltand haltand haltand
and bring their efforts to bear on the thecomplete thecomplete thecomplete
complete reorganization they have havepersistently haepersistently havepersistently
persistently demanded demandedIn In the face 6 6the bthe bf bfthe
the fact that never n ver er in its history has hasthe hasthe hasthe
the American National Red Cross had hatso hadso
so able a management so fine a per personnel personnlI personnel
sonnel as effected at the last annua annuameeting annual annualmtetlng annualmeeting
meeting December S 1888 The reiter reiterated relterattd reiteratcd
ated demands for complete reorganiza reorganization reorgnnlzatlon reorganization
tion ignore the prosont reorganiza reorganizawith reorganlzawith reorganizawith
with a cool audacity that Is both bothamazing bothamazing bothamazing
amazing and amusing</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn89067390/1906-05-17/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=clara+barton+red+cross</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CLARA BARTON ACME,
Red Cross Heroine Will Estab
lish Railroad Hospital Car
Service.
t Although Over Eighty Years Old She
tlu Started In with Great Energy
to Organize New Relict Work to
Cope with Wrecks.
Clara Barton, the famous Red Cross
leader, has Just given new evidence
that she is one of the most remarkable
women the world has ever known. Feol.
Ing that the Red Cross work has been
placed on a permanent basis and no
longer needs ber close supervision, this
untiring woman, although upward of
eighty years of age, has lately returned
to her old home In Massachusetts and
opened headquarters for a great new
movement to alleviate tuffering, name
ly, a project for organizing hospital
corps on all railroads In order that
with the aid of hospital cars speedy
succor may be brought to persons in
jured in wrecks.
The portrait here presented Is ot
especial Interest, inasmuch as It is the
only likeness which Clara Barton has
permitted to be made in many years.
The famous Red Cross worker has no
love for the camera, but her close per
sonal friend, Mrs. John A. Logan, after
much persuasion finally Induced her to
sit for this picture. Mrs. Logan is seen
standing by her side.
WOIi'.'-'D IN CIVIL AND FRANCO
l'UUSSIAN WARS.
Clara Barton, who is entering with
0 much enthusiasm Into a new mls-
MISS CLARA BARTON AND
slonary work, was born In Oxford,
Mass., In 1830. During the Civil War
she did relief work on the battlefields
and organized the search for missing
men for which Congress appropriated
the sum of $15,000. After the close of
that conflict she went abroad and car
ried on the Red Cross activities ot the
Franco-Prussian war, following which
he did heroic work at the Johnstown
flood, distributed relief in the Russian
famine in 1892, and the Armenian mas
sacre of 1896, at the request of the
President of the United States carried
relief to Cuba In 1898, and conducted
the Red Cross relief at the Galveston
flood.
America's most Interesting repre
sentative in the world's group of grand
old women has been loaded with hon
ors by all nstlona, and her home is
filled with valuable tokens of esteem.
Chief among the treasures cherished
by this Idol of conquering armies are
the jewels and decorations tendered her
by the royalty of many nations, and
constituting unquestionably the great
est collection ever bestowed upon any
citizen of the United States.
GIFTS FROM ALL SOVEREIGNS.
Conspicuous In the glittering array
are the amethyst cut In the form ot a
pansy, an Inch and one-hall square,
the gift of Miss Barton's personal
friend, the Grand Duchess of Baden;
the Servian Red Cross decoration pre
sented by Queen Natalie, the Gold
Cross of Remembrance bestowed by the
Grand Duke and Duchess of Baden, a
medal presented by the Queen of Italy,
an English decoration pinned on Miss
Barton's dress by Queen Victoria; the
Iron Cross of Germany presented by
the Emperor and Empress, the decora
tion ot the Order of Meluslne presented
bv the Prince of Jerusalem. Cyprus and
Armenia, and the brooch and pendant
it diamonds, the gift of the people of
'.Johnstown. In recognition of the great
service rendered by Miss Barton after
Mi fafnnns flood.
Miss Barton's father wal In boyhood
jne of the soldiers ot "Mad Anthony
Wayne, and Clarissa Hsrlowe Barton,
a. fipr name Is Inscribe. In the family
Bible, earns to the Bar Stat horns as
a toman Christmas present. Like many
another New England" girl Clara Bar
ton, when thrown on her own resources,
took up school teaching as a means of
livelihood, and when she was obliged
to abandon this because of falling eye
sight, she managed to secure a position
In the Patent Ofllce at Washington, and
here she continued her service until
the outbreak of the Civil War disclosed
to her a llfework. Her advertisements
in the Massachusetts papers that she
would receive money and stores for the
wounded soldiers and personally dis
tribute them at the front brought quick
responses, and from this small beginning
the scope of her "work broadened. The
ministering angel of the Army of the
Potomac was present at the battles ot
Cedar Mountain, the second Bull Run,
Antietam, Fredericksburg and the Wil
derness. WAS WITH THE VANGUARD.
In the Franco-Prussian war Miss
Barton was the first person to enter
Strasburg after the fall ot that city,
and was Instrumental in organizing
the relief. She performed a similar
service at Paris, which she entered with
the vanguard at the conclusion of the
siege. After her return to the United
States she directed relief work in addi
tion to the Instances above mentioned
during the Mississippi flood of 1882, the
overflow of the Ohio River in 1883, the
Louisiana cyclone of the same year,
and the Texas drought of 1889, ever at
the fore aiding, sustaining, and sup
porting by her "Untiring presence the
falling courage of those who In their
suffering learned to depend upon her
with passionate love and gratitude.
Mrs. John A. Logan (Mary Simmer
son Cunningham Logan) who appears
with Clara Barton In this picture, is
a native ot Missouri, but was educated
in Kentucky and married John A. Lo
gan In 1855. Since his death she has
MRS. JOHN A. LOGAN.
engaged in literary work, and has re
sided In the city of Washington, mak
ing her home in a quaint old bouse
filled with mementoes of her hero hus
band. This residence is on a most at
tractive little estate of about one-half
acre In extent, located xn the brow ot
a hill overlooking the nation's capltol.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86099906/1903-02-05/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=clara+barton+red+cross</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CLARA BARTON SARCASTIC.
Red Cross President Takes Mild
Fling at Roosevelt.
San Antonio, Texas,
FRENCH BUILDING, MAIN PLAZA.
BOTICA DEL LE0JSt.
Will practice in the federal and state J W
courts. Laud titles examined.
RHHE2EHEHHS
TV. F. DEKNETTl
Staple Fancy Groceries j
Cigars, smoking and chewing
tohacco, Fancy candies,
cakes and crackers,
Full line tin ware, crockery. Etc.
Washington- Street.
Old Furniture
t&amp;- MADE NEW. -a
i
Joseph Kuek
Cabinet Maker.
J
i. M. H. GROSS
t9MHl.KS1t.ai ItKAB.KXtS fjt
BKOWNSYILLE, Tsxas, and MATAMOE0S, Mexico.
WINCHESTER ARMS ANfi AMMUNITION
.ill
nr
mi
S if. FIELD
-0BALKU
ROGEBIESl
1!
And General Repairer is now ready MP
to repair and upholster furnitnre ii
Levee and lltb. streets. ljT
Shelf and Heavey Hardware,
rAGRI CULTUB.AL IMPLEMENTS
THE TAILOR. W
ELIZABETH STREET.
I am prepared to make snits
and clean Clothes
on -short notice. Work
Guaranteed.
Shop'Opposite Thielen Bakery.
111
Tin aud Wooden Ware,
Wupperman Nou- Breakable
White Enameled Ware,
Sheet Tin and Iron,
Round and Flat Bar Jron,
White Lead, Lubricating Oil,
Turpentine, Paint, Varnish
and Window Oass.
Mixed and Dry Paints for
Carriages and Bnildings,
'Jarriage, Wsgon and Build
mir Material.
Sash, Doors and Blinds to
order:
Lime, Cement and Bricks.
New York, Feb. 1. Replying to
the recent letter of the President's
secretary, George B. Cortelyou, re
questing that public announcement
be made that the President of the
United States and his Cabinet can
not serve as a board of consultation
of the American National Red
Cross, .Miss Clara Barton, president
of the association, has addressed' an
explanatory letter to President
Roosevelt. Referring to article four
of tho constitution of the Red Cross,
providing for a board of consulta
tion, consisting of the President and
his Cabinet and certain high offi
cers of the army, Miss Barton points
out that this provision was full
endorsed by President Arthur and
his entire -cabinet, and accepted by
succeeding administrations. Con
tinuing Miss Barton writes:
"I recite these facts to you, Mr.
President, as an earnest that neither,
was usurpation practiced nor dis
courtesy intended in the late need
ed changes of the article of the con
stitution.
"Thus, Mr. President, if, in the
continuing of -our honored name
and that of your cabinet in our ad
ministration of the Red Cross, I
have committed an error so grave
as to merit a reprimand and be re
quired to make an open denial be
fore the world of privileges, I have
assumed, the powers I have usurp
ed, the disrespect shown the honor
ed heads of the nation and my un
avoidable and deep humiliation
thereat, I shall prove my good citi
zenship by exact and willing con
formity with and obedience to the
commands by the publication of
your honored letter and such re
plies as I have been able to make,
jn order that no misunderstanding
of your relations can possibly oc
cur." The letter concludes thus:"
"Trusting that these concessions,
faithfully submitted, .may prove a
sufficient notice and guarantee to
the public of the disconnection
which you desire from the organi
zation which I have so long had
the pain to conduct, I have the
honor to subscribe myself.
"Your Obedient Countrywoman,
"CLARA BARTON."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1925-10-04/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=clara+barton+red+cross</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Author of Work on Life of Clara
Barton, Red Cross Founder,
Succumbs in Boston.
Charles Sumner Young, the biogra
pher of Clara Barton, died yesterday
In Boston, according to word received
here. Mr. Young had gone to Boston
several years ago, where he organized
the National First Aid Association as
a memorial to Clara Barton, founder
of the American Ked Cross. He was
the author of the ‘•Fife of Clara Bar
ton,” which he published to mark the
centennial of the birth of the famous
Civil War nurse. Two years ago, in
cooperation with the American Tree
Association, he began a campaign for
memorial tree planting In honor of
Clara Barton through all the Brand
Army of the Kepublic posts and the
Women’s Relief Corps organizations
in the United States.
Gen. Nelson A. Miles and Mrs. John
A. Logan, both of whom have since
died, planted a memorial tree for Miss
Barton at Glen Kcho three years ugo.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025294/1903-01-01/ed-1/?sp=57&amp;q=clara+barton+red+cross</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Another of this country's great women
is Clara Barton. Who in America does
not know of Clara Barton, the Red Cross
nurse? But her work was really begun
in England by that wonderful woman
called Florence Nightingale, who was
moved to take tup the work by the fright
ful reports that came into England from
the battlefields during the Crimean war.
After much pleading and insistence this
fragile woman was allowed to go to the
battlefield of Sebastopol and gather into
some sort of shelter the maimed and dying
soldiers, who had been left to rot on the
field as they were. The work there an'
CARRIE CHAPMAN CATT,
P n
Prominent Leader of American Women.
compltislth l rest ltcI i: the w.orlhd cciil
that womaitn wa; Ielled oni the Iittle
fheldI to care for li hie C!i~,t 'Idolw int the
namne of patriotimt. hn. it wa% that the
nations of |utlrolpe INtnio (I encoura:ge thei
training of nur".i out 1i.e the conventst
(for the Sisters f ('l:i: ity hald aready
done good work) to be s.et ,itih thil: ,l.
diers.
CLARA BARTON AND HER
WORK IN OOR OWN WAR
W'hen otur own terrible war spre;idl de
vastation tand dleath ultpotn this cotuntltry
(Ilara lhartoin obtainedi paermi-ioni to
gather at few earinet, .v:f- acriticiiig
womenll togthller and w.:t oitti t, tclinderly
care for the wlounded onl It ilt hlel. It
would lie itmpissile to te l ii a short ar
ticle of this kind vhi't the gentlte min
istering of v.omllent in the war hospittals
was to the foot-sore, wounetiled and d iing
soldiers. blut in our last war ('lara Iar
ton, at the head of the Rled ('ross work,
came again grandly to thle front, and
proved once more that great womenlt are
born to lead great reforms.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87093407/1912-04-12/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=clara+barton+red+cross</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CLARA BARTON, RED
CROSS FOUNDER, DEAD
CLARA BARTON. PHOTO TAKEN ON HER NINETIETH BIRTHDAY
(Mr S*IM Preee I**e*4 Wire)
WASHINGTON. April 12.—Mlsa
Clara Barton, founder of the Nation
al Red Croee movement, died today
at her home in Glen Echo, Md. She
had been ill for months.
Clare Barton *u more than &gt;0
y«*m of age. having baen born In
Oxford, Mun, ta IS2I. Bbe firet
came lmo national promiuenre dnr
in* the rlvil war. »hen ab* partlci
in and directed relief work
on the bsMlefielda. auil alao orkAO
I«h1 !h«- aear&lt; b for iniaainß men for
which congreaa made eitanaive ap-propriation*
After the rloae of the war Mlaa
llarfon a«*oInternational Red OttHM of (ianara.
and aerved in relief work through
out the Franco I'runaian war. finally
uring the adoption of the UM««a
treaty by the I nited Hiataa in IK?.
Ten year* later ahe waa a&lt; 11v«- dur
in( the famine in Rn*ala.
Mi*# Hart on founded and organ
lied the national Red Croaa in thi*
country in I*Bl and remained Ita
preaident until her resignation id
IX&gt;«</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-mabel-stark</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020558/1915-11-04/ed-1/?sp=10&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>This Girl Is Real Chummy Kid

Associates With Lions, And Also Tigers
1
L
ft
v.
jr.
1
Mm
fS fa
4
a
r
h
'A
i
i
4
Miss Mabel Stark
Who educates tigers and lions makes actors of them. Miss star
makes, twice daily, balloon trips with a huge African lion in one
amazing features uf the Al T. Barnes wild animal circus, that will
in Phoenix Tuesday, November
k al.io
of the
exhibit</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88084272/1916-10-24/ed-1/?sp=9&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Miss Mable Stark and Hero.
Miss Mabel Stark, Washing
ington Girl, Has Pet Lion
That Follows Her.
1
A' IILL being the foster mother
r.r a lion Is a most unusual
:h,ng-. and but one instance of
s. i strange affection and rela-
is known. It is that of Miss
Ptark, former society girl of
"-ton, D. C and a. graduate of
"V iE-ton Seminary for Girls.
stark took a motherless lion
cub hut a few dis old. and ly bot
tle, and later by hand feeding-, saved
its life and developed it into a handsome-
t. imn of the Nubian lion.
Mi'- Stark is .itti the AI G. Barnes
Wild Animal circus, which will be here
October 3U-3I.
Not from necess:ty. but through her
love of studying animal psychology.
Miss Stark Is a circus wild animal
trainer, one of the most remarkable,
it is said. In the world. Slight of build,
refined and womanly, she possesses
what seems to be hypnotic power over
the lions ana tigers she handles. The
young woman insists, however, that
it is merely animal psychology put
into practical application.
Nero, the cub which vMiss Stark took
under her care, is now an immense
lion weighing COO pounds, ami he
obeys every order his friend and train
er gives him.
Miss Stark has taught this young
lion to ride a horse, jump through
hoops of fire, work with domestic
animals: in fact, do almost anything
his trainer's fancy dictates.
The beast knows his trainer well
and follows her about. Miss Stark
has frequently led him through city
streets with a dog chain.
The animal has never known any
thing hut caresses, never has felt the
lash, and is as docile with this slip of
a girl as a kitten.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85053058/1917-07-05/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BENGAL TIGERS AND LEOPARDS EDUCATED TO
PERFORM ARE FEATURE OF BARNES CIRCUS

yyr

J
ÊÊ J. -fclSUi
Most fearless woman animal educator in
Circus that she
MABEL STARK.
'kV' WiW Animta</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085187/1918-06-07/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>SOME~DAY
THEY MAY
"GET" HER I
(One of a series of articles
by a Times reporter who Is
traveling il. in i i'i\\&lt;-i
asiiiii-i-,ii wiili Barnes
auliugil circus.)
By Times Reporter.
OBNTRALIA, June 7.—1 stood
at the gate to the arena cage and
watohed Mabel Stark put her Roy
al Bengal tigers thru their tricks.
They were big, ferocious look-
ing beasts and tiiey were never
still. i
The girl trainer, moving in
their midst with a quick, cat-like
tread, scarcely tuned her back
on them for more than a second
at a time.
I noticed that tier eyes moved i
constantly around the ring, from
one tiger to the other, and then
back again, and that all the while
she worked she smiled.
nil.- of Humll reared on his
haunches and struck viciously at i
her. j
She snapped her fingers in his j
face and as he came at her again
t«he stabbed him lightly with tlie
sharp-pronged point of her train-1 1
ing stick. Ii
Cloae Htutvc for Mabel, i
He winced but slightly under |j
the sting of it and struck out
again, this time narrowly missing■
her. j|
Bert Rickman, the bosa of the.i
iring, standing at my side, wliis-i
tied. I
"Nearly got ber that timo." he
commented. "That's tho fellow
that ripped her up so badly in
Detroit. She lias to watch him all'i
I the time. i
"That's the trouble with a
tiger. You can never trust him.
"And he is so quick &gt;ou liave no
warning of what lie is going to do.
|To heat the game you've got to be
jjuat a little bit quicker than they:'
'are and a mighty good reader of i
the big cat's mind."
Hears a (irowl.
Mabel Stark drove her tigers j
one by one fiom tho areua into a i
marrow chute which led out of thej 1
i tent into their wagon cages.
And then witli a little smile at
us she ran across the arena and!
stood with her t&gt;ack to the bars, j
1 noticed that she had thrown her!
whip and prong away. I 1
A low growl attracted my at- i
tention. Opposite the girl, chain- j
ed to the bars, w^ a big Bengal
tiger. I had not noticed him be
fore.
A trainer on the outside of the! 1
jarona cage unleashed him. The!
tiger sprang with a bound the en-li
tire width of the arena. j
I had time to see the girl train-!
er spread out her arms to receive) 1
him when the beast closed in on
her. i
And then they rolled over and i
over, the tiger biting playfully at
her arms and logs, she pulling his
ears and iintiing his nose.
The audience out in front gasp-'1
cd. I could hear the sharp hiss
that told of the quick intake of i
breath. |j
A Knock Over.
"That's a knock over," exclaim-'
ed Ki-okman admiringly. "She
raised that il&gt;rute from a cub. He's
three years old and full grown'
now, but he doesn't know it.
—&lt;"Some day he will and then—"
Rickman halted and ifcFVMti
his shoulders.
"Well," he continupd. "I hope
I'm not in the ring on that night."
The act ended. Miss Stark drovo
her big tiger from the arena. And
joined us.
"How'd you like the act?" she
asked.
"Aren't you afraid that tiger
will turn on you some night?" I
asked.
Mis.* Stank lipsitated and then
replied:
"Some day, yes. But there is
big money in it. And I don't par
f'cularly care. We've all sot to
die some time and I'm taking a
chance."
Uke a Big Buby.
Tonijrht, tomorrow, I may set
mine. But M you saw the tiger
out there this afternoon lie was.
just liko a liig baby playing with j
me. The only danger is that
some day he might realize his tre-1
mendous strength, he might stun
me, or bite me or scratch me and
I might forget and cry out in i&gt;aln I
and show my fear.
"Then it would 'be all off. I
saw a couple of accidents like that
in other shows. Gee, It's force,
too."
Miss StarV made way for a
short, stockily built man in a
white uniform.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88064293/1918-09-21/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Miss Mabel Stark presents
an act with Royal Bengal and Siberian
tigers, the most treacherous animal
known. the trainer's life being in peril
every moment.
High tfehool riding and dancing horses
have a prominent part on the program.
Bob Chocolate, directed by Miss Mabel
Stark, does the tango in approved fash
ion.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96088181/1919-05-09/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A group ot Royal Bengal
tigers and leopards In the hands of
Miss Mabel Stark, amate one with
their learning.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058246/1920-05-04/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text> A group ot
fourteen royal Bengal tigers said to
he the finest specimen evor brought
from India, are to be seen in skilled
ucrobatlc nets under the command of
a beautiful young lady. This young
lady Is Miss Mabel Stark, and is tho
wonder ot tho show world this season
It Is claimed her skill and daring
In 'tho handling of wild beasts has
gained her a seat among the head
liners. Her dexterity In handling
her Royal Bengal tiger nnd sensa
tional act with Rajah, a 300 pound
three year old Royal Bengal tiger
Is nothing more than astounding and
contains enough thrills to appease
the most sensational circus goers.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88086023/1920-05-13/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Royal Bengal tigers are handled by
a oaring woman. She is Miss Mabel
Stark, and is the wonder of the show
world.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90066132/1921-05-02/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Tiny Woman Tames
Monarth of Jungle
Miss Mabel Stark, world's premier
animal trainer, and "Bombay."
one of the recent additions to
the A a. Barnes circus menag
erie, who comes to Salem Satur
day. May 7.
"Rajah," the big yellow-ribbed
Bengal tiger, snarled in cattish
fashion and slunk back into the
shifting-box. He didn't want to
go and flashed his long, four-inch,
yellow.fang teeth to emphasize the
objection. But he had to obey his
trainer and he knew it.
And, what was more to his dis
grace, the trainer was a woman
a little and pretty woman at that.
Her name, the program said, was
Mabel Stark.
Circus patrons, those who at
tend the AJ G. Barnes big four
ring wild animal show, this year,
will get the thrill of their lives
when they see Miss Stark in tht
big steel enclosed ring make twen
tya full score of big yellow
and black jungle prowlers do her
bidding. To the ircus patrons it
will be a distinct and decided
novelty with "a kick," but to the
circus folk themselves as they
watch, It seems a miracle.
For be it known, in the past,
the Royal Bengal tiger the great,
velvety-footed man eater of the
Jungles, has beeil considered un
tamable. Lions and leopards have
for these many years, responded to
the whip-nap of the trainer, but
not his serene highness, the Royal
Bengal. Whether in the deep re
cesses ol the tripical forest or in
the steel- protected cages of the
circus, the big Bengal has remain
ed the monarch. Always has he
defied his arch-enemy man.
And then came "the woman."
She was little, pretty, blonde of
hair, with wide-open blue eyes and
a gentle manner. And yet, Rajah
and his sulking, hulking mates
obeyed her. They wondered why.
Commencing with but a single
tiger, Miss Stark made him do
her bidding. Then she added a
few more. Year by year the num
ber used in the act have Increased
until this year she will present in
the steel ring of the Al G. Barnes
big four-ring trained animal cir
cus, an even twenty. And she will
put them through "stunts" that
not even the faithful and trained
domestic dog could hope to accom
plish. Rajah and his mates snarl;
for why, they ask in their cattish
way, should a Royal Bengal mind
anyone, especially when "that
one" is a woman. But mind they
do. They have to. Little Miss
Stark makes them.
How does she do it? Circus folk
ask the same question. But she
does, and on Saturday, May 7,
when the hig Barnes show comes,
ill may see her.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045774/1921-08-03/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Mabel+Stark+Mary+HaynieRingling+Barnum+Bailey+Circus</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>GIRL JUST MISSES DEATH
IN FIGHT OF THREE TIGERS
Spectators in Panic as Mabel Stark, With Only a Whip,
Protects Herself in Den of Infuriated Circus
Animals in Street Parade.
Special Dispatch to Tub Nbw York Hbbaid.
Aurora, 111., August 2.?A terrific bat- i
tie between a girl and three enraged
tigers, which tool; place in the cage of
a clrcua wagon before hundreds of spec
tators, caused a panic during a parade
yesterday.
While the woman battled alone to
subdue tlie beasts the horses drawing
the wagon became frightened at the
creams of the animals and plunged from
side to side of the street, threatening to
upset the cage and allow the tigers to i
escape among the crowds.
There followed a scramble of men,
women and children to es. ape, and sev
eral persons were trampled In the rush j
before circus roustabouts armed with
long ateel bars succeeded in subduing
the beasts. One of the animals was so
badly Injured that It was shot.
The cage was divided Into two com
partments. In one was a half tamed
tiger and the woman tamer. Mabel Stark
of Louisville. In the other, separated
only by a steel barred door, were two
untamed tigers. The Jar of the wagon
unloosened the fastenings of the door.
As !t swuiut open the battlo started.
Miss Stark, armed only with a whip,
succeeded In fighting the beasts into one
of the compartments and In again bar
ring the door before holp arrived. Then
the tigers battled among '.nemselve*. the
combined efforts of a half dozen circus j
hands being required to separate them</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84031081/1921-10-22/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=mabel+stark+bengal+tiger+rajah</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A PLUCKY GIRL
WRESTLES TIGER
S AS -CIRCUS ACT
Woman has achieved many
startling things In the recent years.
She has Invaded legislative halls
and courts and other hallowed pre
cincts that have always been re
garded as the sole property of mas
culinity. But, Miss Mabel Stark, who Is
coming to Albuquerque Saturday,
October 29, with Al G. Barnes' big
circus, has done more than this.
Not only has she achieved that
which no other woman has ever
done before her, but her feat has
never been accomplished by man
either. She has trained the Bengal
tiger, monarch of the Jungles,
which circus men have long de
clared to be untamable.
Lions and leopards learned years
ago to respond to the crack of the
trainer's whip, but not so the Ben
gal tiger. Always he has defied his
arch enemy man. And he has re
fused to contribute to the enter
tainment of circus-goers except by
appearing behind the bars of a
great steel cage.
Then Miss Stark entered. First
she took a single tiger and worked
with him until, he was willing to
acknowledge her mastery. Then
a .other and another until now she
has a full twenty, all ready to do
her bidding.
Not only does she put the tigers
1 1 V L,nlM r, f ennl, Hn
f ormance of the Barnes circus, but
as a crowning feature she stages a
wrestling contest with "Rajah," a
180-pound Bengal beauty. Some
times Mabel wins, but generally
the decision goes to "Rajah," and
the act is one of the real thrills of
the Barnes performance.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063730/1930-09-15/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=mabel+stark+bengal+tiger+rajah</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>JUST A WRESTLING MATCH
When the Al. G. Barnes Circus appears in this city within a few days
spectators will liave an opportunity to see the greatest woman ani
mal subjugator of all times. M.ss Mabel Stark is the lady in question
nnd she has been the subject of more magazine stories and newspaper
articles than any other woman that ever entered an arena and worked
a ferocious group of jungle beasts. In addition to handling a display
of savage man-killing animals, Miss Stark will also engage in a
wrestling contest with •Rajah.’’ a huge Royal Bengal tiger that weighs
approximately 500 pounds. Miss Stark is the only trainer, either man
or female, with any circus that wrestles a jungle-bred tiger. </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82015313/1929-04-27/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=mabel+stark+bengal+tiger+rajah</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mabel Stark and Ra jah, 250-pound Bengal Tiger.
Bu Time* special
KOKOMO. Ind., April 27—When
the Sells-Floto circus appears here
Monday, its first show in Indiana
after opening the season with a
month's stand in Chicago, the au
dience wilL have an opportunity of
seeing Mabel Stark, famous woman
tiger trainer and her troupe of
striped pets.
Mabel Stark likes tigers so much
that she kept tw’o young ones, Bos
ton and Beauty, in her home, and
they picked the top of a refriger
ator as a place to doze.
One of her acts is wrestling with
Rajah, a 350-pound Bengal tiger,
while she wears a leather suit, not
because it would protect her, should
Rajah suddenly decide she had lived
long enough, but to guard against
unintentional scratches.
The circus will appear in Indian
apolis Tuesday.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82015313/1929-03-15/ed-1/?sp=17&amp;q=mabel+stark+bengal+tiger+rajah</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WOMAN TIGER TRAINER SCOFFS AT DEATH
BY F. BEVERLY KELLEY
PERU, Ind., March 15.—How
would you like to give up a
nice, sedate, dignified occupation
like nursing just to let a flock of
Bengal tigers maul you around
and chew you considerably and
then discover that irate relatives
have cut your picture out of the
family album, so to speak, be
cause your new calling had to do
with a circus?
That is what happened to Mabel
Stark, petite, blond Kentuckian
who is putting sixteen snarling
tigers through their paces every
day at the American Circus Cor
poration winter quarters here in
preparation for the approaching
season under the white tops.
Mabel Stark holds the distinc
tion of being the only woman in
the world who breaks, trains and
works tigers. Her body carries a
hundred scars to indicate that her
climb to stardom in her chosen
profession has not been without
its prifce. Survivor of a score of
battles in the steel arena with
wild animals, she counts a tussel
with a murder-bent Bengal as a
part of the day’s work.
“I’d rather train my ‘kittens'
than do anything else,” explains
Mabel. “Os course, it is danger
ous work and I expect these cats
to finish me some day, but I don’t
take foolish chances. There is no
such thing as a tamed wild
animal."
a a a
MABEL stark trains only
tigers. “They are faster and
make a better showing than
lions,” she contends.
The moth-eaten illusion about
staring a wild animal in the eyes
to subdue him is blasted by this
authority laughingly asks:
“How could I outstare sixteen
tigers at one sitting?” Likewise
is exploded the myth that a
trainer dare not turn his back
on his animals. In Mabel’s act,
there are tigers seated behind and
above her. Rajah is permitted
to spring over his trainer’s bead
while her back is turned.
Curiously enough, this woman
who is so careless with her safety
is tremendously particular about
her personal appearance. She
deplores the countless fine scars
almost invisible on her face. She
refuses to smoke, believing that
nicotine is bad for her complex
ion. All her uniforms are tail
ored to order. Insurance agents
avoid Mabel like small boys avoid
bathtubs. Wild animal trainers
get little attention from the pol
icy salesmen.
When Mabel Stark forsook
nursing to become herself a fre
quent subject for hospitals, all
her relatives promptly elevated
the family nose and added an
other star to the proverbial hea
venly helmet by disowning the
prodical daughter. She had
joined a circus.
She is a widow. Her husband
was a menagerie manager until
his death from heart disease sev
eral years ago.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020558/1919-12-26/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=mabel+stark+bengal+tiger+rajah</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Equally or more spec
tacular was the tiger act given by
Mabel Stark with six of the Bengal
lord of the jungle. The tigers were
just aa unruly as the lions, and then-
mistress seemed in momentary danger
of being bodily devoured every minute
of the act.
As a climax to her act. Miss Stark
appeared In the cage with Rajah, the
king tiger of the circus, and one of the
biggest in captivity, and before the
startled eyes of the audience put on a
wrestling match with the great striped
brute. The slender woman threw the
tiger In straight falls and the tiger
took it good-naturedly.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
